RESUME OF Md. Khairul Bashar

Contact Details: Lalbagh, Dhaka.

Phone:+88-01711 903 622, 01648 849047

E-mail: mamunicma@yahoo.com.



Career Summary:

More than 12 years of practical experience with a diversified professional background in Cost and Management Accountancy. Direct experience of working across Telecom, IGW, ICX, ISP, IIG, Knit Composites Garments, Textile, Yarn Dyeing & All overprinting (AOP) sectors. Successfully introduced & implemented internal control, Auditing, Costing, Budgeting, and budgetary control system as well as practicing management reporting at Mother Color Ltd.

Skills:

Management Accounting
Process design & Re- engineering
Auditing & Internal Control.

Profitability & Variance Analysis Compliance Management New Projects feasibility
Budgeting & Cost Control

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Name of the organization : Mother Color Limited.
Position : GM (Accounts & Finance)

Working since : September, 2016 to March 2020.

Brief Description of Mother Color Limited.

Mother Color Limited is a 100% export-oriented manufacturer & exporter consisting of knitting, Dyeing, Finishing, AOP & garments unit was established in 2004.

Job Responsibilities

Accounts & Finance:

- Supervision of daily, weekly, monthly & yearly finance-related transactions i.e. financial statement (income statement, Balance sheet & cash flow) and report to the management accordingly.
- Established excellent process of revenue, expenditure, financial control systems, and monitoring risk management policies and procedures to minimize enterprise risk & advise top management in capital structure decisions and its effective implementation
- Assessing financial positions of business model periodically and analyzed the business and financial performance on monthly basis against a target
- Studying feasibility/investment analysis for new projects or expansion of existing project.
- Preparing a project profile for getting a bank loan of a new project or expansion existing project.
- Monitoring fund management & working capital as per the Company's policy.
- Performing risk management by analyzing the organization's liabilities and investments.
- Maintaining liaison with external parties.
- Initiating and supervision of Annual Business Plan for the company, including financial forecasts, Business Modeling, and Business risk management.
- Established and maintaining a strong relationship with top management so that identify their needs and seek a full range of business solutions.

Costing & Budgetary Control:

- Introduced & implemented work order wise, buyer wise, fabrics type wise (Knitting), batch & shade wise (Fabric Dyeing & Finishing) and style wise job order costing as well as product pricing.
- Calculation of Monthly CPM, line wise (Garments) production cost & knitting, dyeing & finishing cost.
- Conducting Buyer, Style & order wise profitability analysis.
- Preparation of Monthly & Yearly Budget i.e. Master Budget.
- Find out process loss and the reason for the abnormal loss in various process levels like Knitting, Knit dyeing,
 Finishing process, etc. and control & monitoring the budgetary control system of individual units.
- Monitoring KPI, Efficiency & idle capacity.
- Variance analysis between actual and budget regarding price, quantity of Buyer, style & order.
- Developed Inventory management policy at MCL.

Internal Audit & Control:

- Preparation of monthly & yearly internal audit plan.
- Monitoring follow up audits on a regular interval basis.
- Monitoring operational audits frequently.
- Monitoring various reconciliation I.e. Master LC, Back to Back LC, Accounts receivables & Accounts Payables, etc.
- Monitoring regarding verification of bills, vouchers & various ledgers.
- Frequently conducting market verification for updating day to day financial transactions.
- Established internal control system and procedure in the company to assist in the identification of key risk areas within the business at MCL & evaluated the internal control system and recommend for effectiveness.

Name of the organization : Maxnet ISP, Maxnet IIG, BIGI (IGW), TPNYL. (ICX).

Position : Manager (Accounts & Finance).
Working since : January, 2016 to August 2016.

Brief Description of Maxnet ISP, Maxnet IIG, BIGL, TPYNL.

Maxnet Online Ltd: Maxnet online Ltd. is one of largest ISP who laid approx. 1600 Km of fiber

all over Bangladesh, connecting all division and 47 districts and having few

hundreds of corporate fiber clients.

Maxnet Online: Maxnet online is a Private Limited company with a specific focus on IIG

operation in Bangladesh guided by BTRC. Maxnet online IIG provides

bandwidth to Banglalion, Maxnet ISP and some other.

Bangladesh International Gateway Ltd: BIGL is a licensed International Gateway Operator (IGW) in Bangladesh

providing premium CLI Termination using VOIP & TDM Technology.

<u>Teleplus Neyork Ltd:</u> TPYNL is a licensed Interconnection Exchange (ICX) operator. It routes

national traffic, ISD incoming and outgoing traffics through International

Gate Ways (IGWs) and National Inter Operators.

Job Responsibilities

- Supervision of day to day financial transactions, Accounts Payable, General Ledger and Payroll;
- Preparation of monthly & Yearly financial statements.
- Preparing Monthly & Yearly Budget.
- Preparing & analyzing cost data to facilitate cost effective decision.
- Lead the month-end close process and manage month end reporting to Management.
- Manage annual external audits & liaise with external auditors during audit period;

- Controlling creditors as per fund management
- Recommend and implement strategies to improve Finance and Operations.
- Ensuring all financial transactions are executed and recorded in ERP Systems in a timely manner.
- Providing financial advice by studying operational issues; applying financial principles and practices; developing recommendations.
- Monitoring VAT, TAX, AIT and Customs Duty as per the NBR Regulations.
- Developing external relationships with appropriate contacts, e.g. auditors, legal advisors, bankers and statutory
 organizations such as BTRC, NBR, IOF (IGW OPERATORS' FORUM), BANGLADESH BNAK etc.

Name of organization : Banglalion Communications Ltd.
Position : Manager (Accounts & Finance)
Working since : November, 2012 to December, 2015.

Brief Description of Banglalion Communications Ltd.

Banglalion Communications Ltd. is a fast growing high-speed wimax Internet Company. It is providing 4G internet services in 38 different districts including Dhaka City through 700 wimax towers. Having nationwide license in 2.5 GHz band, it is committed to build a connected Bangladesh through wireless telecom solutions and create a new impact on the business, society, economy & lifestyle of people.

Job Responsibilities

- Preparing Monthly & Yearly Budget of Tower Division, Bcl.
- Introduced Tower wise costing practice.
- Introduced Tower wise profitability analysis.
- Introduced Budgetary control system of Tower Division, Bcl.
- Preparing & analyzing cost data to facilitate cost effective decision.
- Variance analysis between actual and budgeted cost of Tower.
- Taking initiatives when variance is shown unfavorable.
- Managing Fund as per Company's policy.
- Assisting to prepare Annual Business Plan of Tower Division.
- Preparing Monthly Accounts of Tower Division, BCl.
- Checking and reconciliation of various General Ledgers of the books of the accounts.
- Preparing actual & projected Accounts regarding loan.
- Monitoring daily financial transactions.
- Coordinating Sylhet, Chittagong, Khulna, Rajshahi, Rangpur, Barisal, Gazipur, and Narayangonj with responsible persons of accounts department & gather day to day information.
- Controlling creditors as per fund management
- Giving proper guideline to the executives to develop financial recording.
- Enhancing regular improvement of financial activities.
- Performing various analytical tasks as per management's requirement.
- Ensuring of booking revenue on ERP.
- Following up of outstanding bills collections.
- Monitoring Revenue Sharing schedule of BTRC.
- Performing various periodic reports regarding Receivable & Revenue to management.

Name of the Organization : ANLIMA GROUP OF INDUSTRIES

Position : Officer, Accounts

Duration : From 21st June 2008 to 8th November 2009.

Job Responsibilities

- Accounts & Finance:
- Maintaining& Recording Cash & Bank Book.
- Preparing all kinds of Vouchers.
- Bills booking in Tally Software.
- Preparation of Bank reconciliation statement.
- Preparing fund requisition.

QUALIFICATION

Partly qualified Cost and Management Accountant (CMA) – Completed **1700 marks** out of **2000** from the Institute of Cost and Management Accountants of Bangladesh (**ICMAB**).

MBA in Finance: From Darul Ihsan University, Dhaka.CGPA # 3.77. 2008Bachelor of Arts: Kushtia Govt.University College, 2nd Class, 2003.

Higher Secondary Certificate : Kushtia Islamic collage, First Division (Science Group), 1998

Secondary School Certificate : M.A. Bari High School, Chuadanga, First Division (Science Group), 1995

IT KNOWLEDGE

- Experienced in ERP environment
- Have good hands in accounting software i.e. Tally, AccPac
- Have good hands in IT and MS application.

PERSONAL DETAILS

Father's Name : Md. Abdul Khaleque

Mother's Name : Mrs. Hasina Begum

Permanent Address : Village-Bohirgachi, P.O.-Joydia,

P.S. - Coat Chandpur, Dist. Jhenaidah.

Marital Status : Married

Religion : Islam (Sunni).

Nationality : Bangladeshi.

Blood Group : O+
Sex : Male.

REFERENCE

M.A. Salam FCMA General Manager (F & A) & Company Secretary AKS Khan Holdings Ltd Rypayan Prime, House 02, Road, 07, Dhanmondi Dhaka

Mobile: 01811-447324

......

Md.Khairul Bashar

Date: